# **SARTHAK VAJPAYEE**

# Dallas, TX 75248 | 469-347-9198 | sxv220020@utdallas.edu | WWW: Online Digital Resume

# Website, Portfolio, Profiles

- https://sarthakv7.github.io/my\_folio/
- https://github.com/SarthakV7
- https://www.linkedin.com/in/sarthak-vajpayee/

# **Professional Summary**

Well-qualified Data Scientist experienced working with vast data sets to break down information, gather relevant points and solve advanced business problems. Skilled in predictive modeling, data mining and hypothetical testing. Offering 4 years of experience in improving business operations.

#### Skills

- Data Analysis & Data Mining: Scikit-Learn
- Probability & Statistics, Multivariate Calculus & Linear Algebra
- Machine Learning & Deep Learning
- Tensorflow, Keras, PyTorch
- Python, MySQL, MongoDB, PySpark
- Computer Vision, Natural Language Processing (NLP)

- Data Visualization
- Git, Docker, Spacy, NLTK, Plotly, OpenCV
- Data Wrangling
- Cloud Computing (AWS & GCP)
- Demand Forecasting
- Good Communication Skills

# Work History

#### **Senior Data Scientist**

12/2021 to 07/2022

#### Ernst & Young Global Limited – Bengaluru, India

- Designed **predictive modeling** framework for world's 3rd largest FMCG, which achieved an **accuracy** of over **90%** and **bias** under **15%**, **outperforming** previous demand planning techniques across all categories in the Nordics market.
- Delivered Gen-2 version (70% Volume and SKU coverage) for the Norwegian market within 15 days, benchmarking among European, South-East Asian, and South American markets.
- Built automated **data discovery** streams and **data pipelines** and implemented code **modularization** along with **E2E testing** for production on **Azure Data-Lake** utilizing **Apache Spark** and **Python**.
- Leveraged highly **intermittent time-series** data sources to extract deep insights on demand, such as previous sales, interior trends, external trends, events, and promotions.
- Performed regression and variation analysis across different FMCG categories and conducted exploratory data analysis on variables, such as product volume and market cannibalization.

# **Machine Learning Engineer**

09/2019 to 11/2021

Applied Roots – Hyderabad, India

- **Designed, released,** and **maintained** six **python** based **Machine Learning** and **Deep Learning** projects in Applied Roots (an e-learning platform), along with mentoring and evaluating assignments of over **8000 students**.
- Contributed to **100% year-over-year** revenue growth by creating **operational strategies** and technical development of the platform.
- Designed plagiarism checker for student coursework by leveraging various NLP and Deep Learning

techniques such as Word-to-Vector, Code-to-Vector, Pre-trained Language Models, and LSTM.

## **Research Project Assistant**

03/2021 to 11/2021

Stellenbosch University – Stellenbosch, South Africa

- Designed, trained, fine-tuned, and validated several deep-learning and transfer-learning based models such as MLP, RNN, CNN, VGG-16, and RESNET-50 for predicting COVID-19 using patient's cough audio.
- Achieved specificity, sensitivity, AUC, and accuracy scores of 0.9, 0.93, 0.96, and 92.78% resp. Using RESNET-50 model, making COVID-19 diagnostic through this tool on par with the RT-PCR test.
- Developed **web-application** using **Python** and **Javascript** for users to get diagnosed with COVID-19 **within 5 seconds** through their cough audio.

#### Freelance Data Scientist

10/2020 to 01/2021

ViVi Green Innovators (Viscon Group) – Amsterdam, Netherlands

- Utilized python and image processing for object skeletonization, localization, and unsupervised
  machine learning (DBSCAN clustering) to develop and test a machine vision and robotic process
  automation-based product for extraction of plant cuttings, used in horticulture for vegetative
  (asexual) propagation.
- Developed and delivered a prototype within 70% of deadline duration with 5/5 client satisfaction.

## Education

Master of Science: Business Analytics (Data Science Specialization)

Expected in 05/2024

University of Texas At Dallas - Dallas, TX

**Bachelor of Technology**: Electronics And Communications Engineering

06/2018

JSS Academy of Technical Education - Noida, India

# Certifications

- Google Cloud: Advanced machine learning on Google Cloud specialization.
- Coursera: Deep-learning specialization.
- Applied roots: Certified Data Scientist.
- Udacity: Al for Trading Nanodegree.
- Stanford University: Machine learning.
- Amazon: Machine learning on AWS.